There's a major shift happening in AI
first development right now. And if
you've been watching my channel, you
know I've been talking about this for
months. Spec driven development. This is
how professional builders move away from
the unpredictability of vibe coding into
a workflow that actually ships. It's a
methodical approach that takes your
product from idea to customer
consistently. And for me as a business
owner and a product designer, it's what
has me fired up about this moment. We're
not just changing how we code, we're
changing how we build. So a few months
ago on this channel, I introduced spec
driven development along with agent OS.
That's my free open-source system for
powering a specdriven process. And now
we're seeing the big toolmakers are
converging on the same realization that
a specdriven approach is the way. And I
love this direction that we're going in
as an industry. Just this week, GitHub
launched their spec kit project. Amazon
recently released Kirao, which is built
around planning with specs. Cursor added
some task tracking stuff to their UI.
Cloud code has had planning mode. So,
we're seeing this spec driven approach
make its way into the mainstream tools.
And again, the industry is broadly
getting on the page that specs are
essential, but the tooling and process
behind specri development is still
pretty unsettled. And honestly, that's
good. We're all still figuring out what
it means to build in the AI first era.
Today I want to examine specri
development in the real world because
there are three critical aspects that I
think the mass market tooling is still
missing and if we don't address these AI
adoption with our teams will continue to
be an uphill battle. I'm Brian Castle. I
help professionals stay ahead with
practical AI strategies and every week I
send out my builder briefing. That's a
fiveminute read to help keep you sharp.
You can get yours by going to
buildermethods.com
and subscribers are always the first to
hear about my next live workshop where
we talk about what's working with AI. So
for the last few months as I've been
applying specdriven development in my
own products and watching the tooling
evolve, I've noticed three fundamental
problems that most tools aren't
addressing. These are things that I try
to solve as I iterate on agent OS. And
I'll show you how I use that to make my
specs actually useful. So the first
issue is a lack of process for
establishing alignment. So most tools
just expect you to show up with a prompt
and generate a spec as if they
inherently know what you want and how
that's supposed to fit in the bigger
picture of your product. But we don't
just wake up knowing what to build. Even
when we know what the next feature on
our road map is, there's still a crucial
phase before creating the spec. And that
involves deciding on the right approach,
hashing out the trade-offs, the design
decisions, the edge cases, your product
strategy. Because we know there are
always multiple ways to build the same
feature. The question is which way is
best for your product and your
customers. So the newest version of
Agent OS doesn't rush into writing your
specs. Instead, first it has your agent
work with you on ideiation and strategic
planning. This foundational context is
critical if you want agents to build an
alignment with your vision. Let me show
you what this looks like. So, I'm
working on a simple app called
flashcards so that I can quiz my kids on
their homework assignments. And in here
in the agent OS folder, I have my specs
folder. Now, I've already built out the
first uh feature and that's the finished
spec right there. So, let's go ahead and
start the next spec. I've got Cloud Code
open here and I'm going to start with
new spec. Just going to run the new spec
command. Now, if you're familiar with
agent OS, you know that I already have
my uh product plan with the road map and
mission built in. So, uh agent OS did
reference that and it's asking me if I
want to uh just build the next item in
my road map and I can check my road map
here.
So, we've already built out uh these two
parts and now we need to build out the
question builder interface for multiple
choice questions. Let's go with that. So
now it's using sub aents for every step
in the process if you're using cloud
code which supports sub aents and you
can see that we've now built out the
folder for the next spec. That's the
question builder interface and we're
initializing here. Okay. So now it has
passed the baton onto the spec
researcher sub aent and that one is here
to help me research and plan and hash
out the details for this new feature
before we even get into writing the
spec. So, as you can see, it came up
with a list of clarifying questions. Uh,
looks like we have nine of them. I just
want to point out that built into agent
OS, I've instructed the agent to analyze
my mission, my product road map, my
standards, and the initial idea for what
this feature is going to be, and then to
come up with clarifying questions.
Specifically, I told it to number them,
which is going to make it easy for me to
just answer, you know, number one
answer, number two, answer, number
three. The other thing that I said was I
wanted to ask the questions and then
provide a sensible assumption as the
probable answer to the questions. And
that makes it really easy for me to just
do things like number one, yes, number
two, yes, number three, let me course
correct a little bit, number four, yes.
So, you know, just making the process of
planning and ideulating and hashing out
a little bit easier than for me to have
to come up with these questions on my
own. And one more tip, I also emphasized
the importance of referencing
pre-existing design elements and
architectural elements in the codebase
itself um when it's coming up with these
questions. And uh as you can see down
here we have a section where it asks me
literally are we going to be reusing any
existing code or you know components in
the uh codebase. So this is all really
important planning material that should
go into the process. So let me go
through and answer these questions.
Okay. So I've added my answers to
questions 1 through nine. As you can see
it's really easy for me to just confirm
the uh assumption that the agent made
and make some very minor uh course
corrections. I forgot to add the note
about uh existing reuse. Um
so I'm saying like reuse our existing
styling around the the existing
questions UI that we have. And then
there's one final thing that agent OS
asks for. Now we have a visuals folder.
And this is optional, but if you have
any sort of mockups or wireframes, now
is a great time to put them into the
planning. Agents work so much better
when they get to follow an actual visual
reference. And uh I do have a very
simple um rough wireframe. I'm going to
just drop that into the visuals folder.
So we have that in the planning for this
spec. And we also have it built in to
recognize whether this is a detailed
mockup versus just a rough wireframe. In
this case, it's going to know that it's
a wireframe. Okay. So I think we're good
on my initial questions and I'm going to
send those along. All right. So we're
not done yet. Uh, the agent just
analyzed both my answers to the first
set of questions and it took a look at
the wireframe that I provided it and it
came up with a couple additional
clarifying questions just to really make
sure that we're on the same page. It
noticed something that I put into my
visual wireframe and it wants to confirm
the direction here. It even pointed out
that I forgot to mock up a detail to,
you know, select which is the default
answer.
And again, it worded them in ways that
make it really easy for me to quickly
respond. It says like, would you like to
do it this way or that way? And I can
just say option A, you know. Okay, so
the spec researchers work is done. And
let's see what we have so far. So again,
we're we're inside the spec folder. We
have not created the actual spec yet,
but so far we have this planning folder.
Inside that we've got our visual, that's
our wireframe, and we have this
initialization. This is just very
simple. was, you know, just to record my
very first direction. And then we have
this requirements document. It it just
serves as a reference and a record of
the discussion that we had each question
that the agent asked me uh what my
answers were and um it has the follow-up
questions. it, you know, references some
existing code and it has some notes on
the visual assets and it analyzed them
and and gave itself some notes on what
it found some visual insights,
functional requirements. So again, I can
like even go through here and just
double check that all these details are
in fact correct. You know, I might check
things like, did I actually answer the
right thing? Or do I want to rethink
certain details about how this feature
should be designed? Or I might want to
check to see the agent actually
interpreted what I had to say correctly
because a lot of this stuff is, you
know, notes in the agent's words, not
mine. I'll go through and double check
these, but again, like this is sort of
like the raw material, the strategic and
design decisionm that together we've
come up with. And now it's sort of in
the context, but we also have it
documented here in the folder. So now I
can proceed with the actual creation of
the spec with much higher confidence
that the content of the spec is going to
be exactly what I want. Look, this is
where our craft happens. Now, of course,
we know how our code is going to fit
together, but our agents can build most
of that. Where we bring value is through
design and our taste and experience and
understanding what our customers need.
That happens here in the planning phase.
All right. Now, while the spec writer
sub agent is writing up our spec, I want
to talk about the second big issue that
I'm seeing and that's missing context
about your standards. So, in order to
write specs that ensure agents will
build correctly the first time, we need
granularity about how the code should be
written. So just telling our agent to
build a React app or build a Rails app,
that's not enough. There are countless
variables, your text stack, your code
style, your existing libraries,
established patterns, components,
layouts that you've already developed.
We need our specs to instruct our agents
to adhere to all of these directions.
And we can't just assume that their
quick codebase scan is going to pick up
everything. We also can't just retrain
our agents on every new feature that
they develop because then we're just
back to prompting in circles. So, as
I've shown in my previous videos
covering agent OS, it lets you define
your coding standards and your design
choices and your common patterns once.
So, when your specs get written and your
code gets implemented, your agents
already have that knowledge baked in.
So, it looks like our spec is almost
ready. The spec writer finished its work
and now it passed the baton onto our
spec verifier which is checking the spec
writer's work, making sure that it's all
accurate, that we uh crossed our tees
and dotted our eyes, if you will, and
that's all set. So, here is everything
that it did. So, let's go ahead and take
a look. So, now we have our official
spec.md. Now, I used to have a much more
complex version of this, but I purposely
had the agent simplify it down to just a
one-pager. We've got the goal. We've got
a couple of user stories, some
functional requirements, some
nonfunctional requirements. Uh then we
have some notes on the visual design
referencing the uh the visual that I had
provided. We're also calling out to some
reusable components that already exist
in the codebase so that you know the
agent can leverage those and not rebuild
the same thing twice. We've got some
notes on the technical approach. This is
intentionally not going into great
detail because, you know, we still want
to let the actual coding agent and the
specialist sub agents that are going to
be uh responsible for these items sort
of do their thing rather than leading
them down potentially the wrong path up
front. So, you know, this is just the
highle specification, but it is highly
accurate. As you can see, there are now
multiple layers at play here. We did the
initial Q&A and clarifying and and
hashing out of the details. Then it went
through and and created the uh the
specification which also took into
account my standards that are built into
agent OS and we had the verifier agent
come in and and look at it all and now
I'm putting my human eyes on it as well.
So we've got our spec and then we have
our tasks. So this is the actual task
list that would be implemented once we
get to the implementation phase. It is
broken out into task groups each with a
main parent task and some subtasks. The
other thing that you'll notice is that
agent OS is suggesting which sub aent
like in this case doing the database
updates that's going to go to the
database engineer sub aent and getting
down into the API layer that'll go to
the API engineer. Um so we're grouping
these into groups of tasks that
individual sub aents can tackle sort of
like separately and that'll be really
useful when it comes to implementation.
You know, here we're going to work on
the UI. So, we're going to delegate to
the UI designer sub agent. So, you know,
agent OS 2.0 when you're using it with
cloud code is going to be heavily built
around this idea of orchestrating
multiple sub aents to pick off each
individual uh task group when it comes
to implementation. Now, of course, I I
can still review these tasks. I can even
review which agent it's planning on
delegating to. Um, and these are things
that I can tweak and change on the fly.
like this particular feature might be
built a little bit differently than the
last feature that I built or I might be
doing things a little bit different in
this project versus a different project.
And so agent OS gives me that
flexibility to spin up different types
of sub aents and incorporate them into
my process in different ways depending
on the project. And in fact, that brings
me to the third and I think the most
important factor when it comes to real
world adoption of these AI tools and
spec driven development and that is the
tooling can't be too rigid about
defining our development process.
Because look, we all build differently.
Your team might take an API first
approach. Mine might emphasize UI first.
You might have 30 engineers in a
department or she might be working at a
startup with three co-founders. His team
over there might have multiple testing
phases. Hers prioritizes getting a
product out to customers quickly. And
each feature in your product might be
built a little bit differently. One
might involve a lot of API and database
changes and the next feature might focus
more on UI and the one after that might
just concern the mobile app. Each spec
involves different sub aents and a
different mix of phases in your
development process. You know, if your
tooling adds friction as you or your
team is moving between different
features, different products, that can
prevent full adoption of specd- driven
development, and then you'll miss out on
the benefits and the leverage that AI
first development has to offer. So, in
designing the newest version of Agent
OS, one of my goals is to make it as
adaptable as your development process
requires. It leverages sub agents and
orchestration that you can control as
you move between specs. So, I'll be
sharing my latest patterns in spectriven
development and in agent OS in my next
live workshop and in my builder briefing
newsletter. So, you can get on that by
going to buildermethods.com.
And speaking of patterns, now that we're
rethinking what it means to build and
ship products, it's easy to lose that
sense of flow that we used to have when
we were deep in our code bases before
all these AI agents came along. But I
think it's still possible to achieve
that flow state, which can lead to
breakthroughs in your product. You can
see my recent video on finding flow with
spec driven development. And so after
you hit that subscribe button, head over
there, check that one out next, and
let's keep building.